Cursor just released a new feature
called the visual editor, which is part
of their built-in browser that came in
with Cursor 2.0. It lets you click
elements, drag things around, and tweak
CSS properties visually. And you might
be thinking, "Cool demo, but that's
another feature that I'll never actually
use." And honestly, for most of my
workflow, that's probably true. But
there's one specific phase of
development where I can actually see
myself reaching for this tool. And
today, I want to show you what that
workflow looks like. And I also want to
talk about what this tool doesn't do and
what I think is still the missing piece
when it comes to designing new apps and
interfaces in this AI-first era. Now, a
quick thing before we dive in, I'm Brian
Castle, and every Friday I send my
Builder Briefing. It's a 5-minute read
to help you adapt your craft and your
mindset as building with AI becomes the
norm. To get on that, head over to
buildermethods.com.
And if you're subscribed, then you'll
hear about my live workshops, where this
month I'm covering the AI-first design
process. All right. Now, before I open
up Cursor and show you this new visual
editor, I want to step back for a
second. A year ago, Cursor was just a
code editor, a somewhat interesting fork
of VS Code. But today, they've got plan
mode, background agents, mobile access,
a built-in browser, and now this visual
editor. So, if you're following this
space, then you're seeing how they're
breaking down barriers between
traditional roles, designers,
developers, product managers. We've all
had our separate tools. Cursor seems to
be building toward a single environment
where all that work can happen. And so,
I'd like to pay attention to how these
major tool companies are pushing
boundaries because it it has a real
impact on how we adapt our workflows in
this era of building with AI. Okay,
enough high-level, let's take a look at
this visual editor in Cursor. All right.
So, I'm here in Cursor, and I'm working
on my buildermethods.com
site and membership app. It's a Rails
app. And I'm already running the server
here. So, I'm going to fire up the
built-in browser. Command-Shift-B is my
shortcut for that. Let's clean up my
window layout here. I'm going to hide
basically everything so that I can just
see the full built-in browser here in
Cursor. So, this was a new feature that
came in with Cursor 2.0, and I did an
entire video breakdown on my favorite
features of Cursor 2.0 just a couple
weeks ago. The browser is one of them,
and you know, they had this feature
already where you can sort of target
individual individual elements on the
page.
And that made it really easy to just
grab an element, and you know, if you
open up your agent, you can you can grab
an element and reference it right in the
chat, and then you can sort of prompt
based on that. So, that's not new, but
what is new is this new visual editor.
So, if you click this icon right here,
you'll pull open this new design
sidebar. So, again, you can like select
any individual element on the page. It
gives you sort of a map of the
components there. I don't know how
actually useful that is in in my case.
But what is kind of useful is going
through all these design settings, which
are essentially easy controls to tweak
CSS properties. You can see exactly what
CSS is being rendered on the the element
that you have selected here by
inspecting that, similar to how you
would inspect the CSS in something like
Chrome DevTools. But you can go in here,
and and you can sort of tweak different
settings. So, so for example, you know,
these three text elements I have sort of
in a container, and that's using like a
like a flex layout. You can tweak the
alignment. So, instead of it them being
left-aligned, I can make them centered
or right-aligned. I can tweak the the
gap between these elements. I can do all
sorts of like easy stuff. Now, you know,
when I'm refining a design, these are
the types of things that I often do.
Actually, like refining that gap between
elements is something that that I do
quite often when I'm when I'm like doing
these like final design refinements. And
I think that's a key way to think about
this tool, and and I'll touch on that
more in a few minutes. Now, you can also
select an entire element and actually
drag it around the interface. So, for
example, if I want to like sort of like
reorder these. Now, I think that this
would really depend on how your DOM and
your CSS is already structured on your
page, and that'll that'll define like
how easy it is to actually move elements
around. So, let's see if I can like mess
with my signature, and you know, like I
have I have this letter sort of in its
own container, which makes it a little
bit difficult to just drop that in the
middle of the letter, which is not
something I would normally actually want
to do, but just to show you, you are
sort of constrained to your existing DOM
structure, your HTML structure, and CSS
structure that's on the page. Which
actually, I think is a probably a pretty
good thing to have that constraint in
place. Now, another interesting feature
here as I dig into some of these
controls is, you know, anything that
deals with colors, you can choose you
can click this button where it says
choose token. So, for example, let's
look at this this button here. We can
tweak the background to something
something like that, which is not
exactly something I want to do, but but
it says choose token. And so, by these
design tokens, it means that it's
finding these colors that exist. These
are like, you know, these appear to be
Tailwind CSS colors. Now, the selection
of colors, I think, is interesting. It
found the existing colors that I'm using
somewhere on this page, but it also
found a couple of the of the custom like
color definitions that I've defined in
my codebase. So, in this particular
site, I do have a color like a design
color system where I've defined a
primary color and
color. Now, I did not specifically
design these other colors like violet,
yellow, you know, rose,
emerald. Those are sort of just like
Tailwind colors that it found somewhere
on this page or or maybe somewhere in my
codebase. And it sort of mixed and
matched that. I actually don't know how
much I like that piece of it, you know,
because in my in this particular
codebase, I do have a very specific
design system. And like this is a a
Tailwind CSS theme that I've applied to
my site where I I I've only defined a
secondary, tertiary, gray, actually also
a primary, and and a black color. And I
like I like limiting my color palette to
keep the branding intact, to keep this
design system intact. And you know, this
visual editor, I must say, you know,
almost gives me a little bit too much
flexibility to to play with colors
because that can really like make my
design system become inconsistent
throughout my site or my app. So, I
would actually like to see a little bit
more control over
which over exactly which colors or or
which branding system I'm making
available here in the in the visual
design editor. I think from a design
standpoint, it's really help it's it's
really helpful not to have unlimited
flexibility or unlimited options, but to
actually intentionally provide some some
restraints, some guardrails to keep your
design tight and consistent, especially
from a branding perspective. Now,
clearly, this feature is not designed to
replace your entire design workflow.
What this visual editor is really good
at is refinement, that final polish
phase where you've already got a design
in place, and you're just tweaking
things to make them pixel perfect. You
know, members of my Builder Methods Pro
membership have seen me teach the
Builder Method, and that has three main
phases: design, build, and refine. And
this visual editor from Cursor slots
perfectly into that third phase, the
refine phase. Now, when it comes to that
last mile of refining an interface, I
typically use one of two methods. Either
I speak my prompts into my coding agent
and have it rapidly fix those design
details. And actually, the Composer
model from Cursor is really great at
this because it works so fast. Or I
would open up Chrome DevTools and
inspect elements and then handwrite the
adjustments to CSS properties right
there in the console so that I can
visually see them. And then I would
screenshot them and then hand that
screenshot to my coding agent to
implement the change. And this visual
editor in Cursor seems to combine both
of those approaches and make that whole
workflow even more efficient. So, I
expect that this is something that I'll
start reaching for a lot going forward.
Now, I want to be clear about what
Cursor's visual editor is designed to be
and what it's not. It's a tool for
adjusting existing designs, but it's not
a tool for creating new ones. Let me
show you what I mean. All right. So, I'm
back in Cursor. I'm looking at a page in
the built-in browser. I've got the
visual editor open here. And you know,
when I first started playing around with
this, I started to try to do things
like, you know, grabbing an element like
like one of these benefits here. And I
thought that maybe I'd be able to copy
it like Command-C and Command-V and and
do something like that, or maybe like
Command-D to duplicate it. But that kind
of stuff does not work. It's funny how I
was reaching for shortcuts that I would
normally use in a design tool cuz that's
what this visual editor makes me feel
like I'm using. I would expect to be
able to create new pieces of of UI, or
at the very least, copy and duplicate
elements on the page. We can't quite do
that using the visual editor in Cursor,
at least not today.
But the closest thing that we can get to
that is doing, you know, something like
this where if we sort of like select one
of these one of these elements, at least
that can help me get that element right
into the the agent chat. And you know,
for this, I'm not even going to be using
the the visual editor piece of it, but I
am easily just referencing that element
that I just selected, and I can just say
something like, you know, do
duplicate this element, even though I
spelled that wrong.
You know, I love the Composer model here
in Cursor because it does quick design
changes like this super fast. Now,
what's interesting here is that it
actually did make the change, right? So,
I could I could like literally see the
change has happened. I could see this it
has actually added the new testimonial
right there. But you know, in order to
actually see that change show up in the
browser in Cursor, I need to I still
need to like manually refresh the
browser, and now I see the additional
element that was added to the page. Now,
I'm not I'm not exactly sure if the
built-in browser in Cursor has a hot
reload where like as soon as you make a
change, it'll show up in the browser.
That wasn't the case here. That might
have been a case an issue with my code
base, but I don't think that that's a
feature that they have quite yet in the
built-in browser. Maybe they will soon.
Uh so then then it would act more like a
true What's the old-school term for
that? WYSIWYG, what you see is what you
get. But under the hood, at the end of
the day, we are still deciding to make
changes first, prompting the agent to
make those changes in code, and then
refreshing to see those changes in the
browser. Now, don't get me wrong. I'm
not looking for Cursor to become a
modern-day Dreamweaver or mimic a
traditional design tool like Figma. I'm
just pointing out that I like Cursor's
visual editor for what it is. It's a
refinement tool, not a creation tool.
So, if you're trying to figure out what
your new product should even look like,
the layout, the visual hierarchy, the
overall aesthetic, that's a different
problem. And that's one that I think a
lot of us are still trying to figure out
in this AI-first era. Because
traditionally, a designer would first
create mockups by hand in Figma, and
then someone would convert that to code.
Now, our agents can design and build
front end and back end all at the same
time. But is that actually the best
approach? Or is that what makes vibe
coding so messy and unprofessional?
Well, this month I'm releasing something
totally new called Design OS. It fills
that missing design phase between having
an idea for a product and handing it off
to your coding agent. approaches design
in a way that actually makes sense for
how we build with AI now. If you want to
see this new AI-first design process
with Design OS, my next video will give
you that full walk-through. It's also
the topic of my live workshop happening
this month. So, right after you hit
subscribe on this channel, check out my
next video on AI-first design with
Design OS. Let's keep building.